<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the supreme authority of the nation, the Parliament of the Common-Wealth of England. The humble petition of the Lord Mayor, aldermen, and commons of the City of London, in Common Councell assembled.</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E712_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207140</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866211</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94695)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 110:E712[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the supreme authority of the nation, the Parliament of the Common-Wealth of England. The humble petition of the Lord Mayor, aldermen, and commons of the City of London, in Common Councell assembled.</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 4, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Flesher, printer to the Honourable City of London.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes Parliament's answer, dated 2 Sept. 1653.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept. 3:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118476:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO THE Supreme Authority of the Nation, THE PARLIAMENT OF THE COMMON-WEALTH OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>THE Humble Petition of the Lord Mayor, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Commons of the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> in Common Councell aſſembled.</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>James Fleſher,</hi> Printer to the Honourable City of <hi>London.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:118476:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118476:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Supreme Authority of the Nation, THE PARLIAMENT OF The Commonwealth of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The humble Petition of the Lord Mayor, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Commons of the City of <hi>London</hi> in Common Councell aſſembled.</head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p>THAT your Petitioners doe in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and thankfulneſſe acknowledge the infinite goodneſſe of God to this Nation, in the free paſſage of the Goſpel for neer one hundred years together; and the Peace, Plenty, and Proſperity that it hath brought with it: and that all along God hath raiſed up Pious, Learned, and Painfull Preachers of the Goſpel, whoſe labours God hath bleſſed in the converting of Thouſands, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of the truth againſt Popery, Errors, and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, although very much oppoſed and perſecuted by a Popiſh, Prelaticall Party.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118476:3"/>
            <p>Your Petitioners doe likewiſe acknowledge (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many worthy things done by the late Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament) the tender care they had of all able, faithfully godly Miniſters, in ſetting them at liberty from their former Perſecutors, and giving them all Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Exerciſe of their Miniſtery, and by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding towards their maintenance a conſiderable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue over and above what was anciently ſetled by Law; They alſo incouraged Learning, by reforming the Unive<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſities, and increaſing the maintenance of the Governours of Colledges, where there was need; And what a mercy is it like to prove to the Nation, there being ſo many hopefull Plants, that in a ſhort time (by the bleſsing of God) may be fit for publike ſervice: And while they were thus promoting the Intereſt of Chriſt, how did the Lord bleſſe their Councels and Forces by Land and Sea, to the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Friends and Enemies both at home and abroad?</p>
            <p>But as heretofore there never wanted Inſtruments to vilifie, oppoſe, perſecute or undermine the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters, and preaching of the Goſpel, ſo of late years, yea, at this day, what ſcorn and contempt is caſt upon them? and what endevours are uſed by Petitioning and otherwiſe to deſtroy the Univerſities, and undermine the Preaching of the Goſpel, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away that ancient ſetled Maintenance which hath been Owned and Acknowledged as their due, by all Parliaments and Courts of Juſtice time out of minde: And if the Jeſuites, and thoſe that are Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly affected (of which we have cauſe to fear there are many in this Nation) ſucceed in their preſent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118476:3"/> Councels and Practices and diſaffecting the Nation, to the Univerſities and Learning, and the profitable uſe of it, in the Preaching of the Goſpel, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting errors; And likewiſe ſhall prevail in removing the preſent ſetled maintenance which is earneſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devoured by them; And perſwade that the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate hath nothing to doe in matters of Religion: They will then be in a very great forwardneſſe to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that deſign they have had againſt this Nation, ever ſince the firſt Reformation from Popery.</p>
            <p>Now though the Conſideration of all theſe things lies ſad upon our hearts, we cannot but with than<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe acknowledge that there is a ſupreme Power over us, to whom we have incouragement to make our humble addreſſe; Who have been pleaſed ſo publickly and affectionately to declare, That you will be as tender of the Lives, eſtates, Liberties, juſt rights and proprieties of all others as ye will be of your own and of your Poſterities. And further that you cannot but acknowledge that ye are not yet at reſt, nor can believe ye have yet enjoyed or ſeen enough to accompliſh the end of God, or ſatisfie the thoughts of men, for that vaſt expence of blood and Treaſure which could not have been endured with any patience; But in hope, that at length thoſe bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pangs and throwes would make ſome way for that long expected birth of Peace, Freedome, and Happineſſe, both to the ſouls and bodies of the Lords people; And while we are waiting for the fruit of ſuch pious reſolutions, it cannot but be much grief of heart, and regret of ſpirit to your Petitioners, to have this Parliament unworthily traduced and reflected
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118476:4"/> upon by ſome perſons which we humbly conceive, do directly tend to the gratifying of the common enemy, the raiſing of Sedition, diſturbing of the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and deſtruction of this Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The premiſes conſidered,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Petitioners doe humbly pray, that care be taken that the pretious truths of the Goſpel, which hath been the bleſſed portion of this Nation ſo many years, may be preſerved in their purity, that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpenſers thereof, being men Learned, Godly, and void of offence, may receive all due incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And that ſuch (being ſo approved) may be ſent forth to preach the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>That the ſetled maintenance by the Laws of the Land for them, may be further confirmed; And that the Acts and Ordinances of Parliament formerly made to this purpoſe may be put in execution: and ſuch other proviſion made that their juſt proprieties may be preſerved.</p>
            <p>That the Univerſities alſo that are the Seminaries of all ſorts of Litrature, ſo eminently uſefull for this Common-wealth; both in reſpect of Civill Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and alſo the propagating and defending the bleſſed truths of the Goſpel, may be zealouſly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced and incouraged,</p>
            <closer>All which we humbly ſubmit to your Grave and Pious conſideration And ſhall ever pray.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="comment_on_disposition_of_petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:118476:4"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Friday the 2<hi rend="sup">
                        <hi>d</hi>
                     </hi> of September 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Petitioners were called in, and being come to the Barre M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Speaker by Command of the Houſe did return thanks to the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for their good affections to the Parliament, and acquainted them that ſome of the matters in the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are under conſideration, and as touching that which concerns the traducing the Parliament, the Petitioners are referred to the Councell of State to give Informations to them therein, and that the Parliament doth not doubt but they will continue their care of the Peace and ſafety of the City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Hen: Scobell</hi> Clerke of the Parliament.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
